Voiced consonants and reduced vowels The strong intonation in American English
creates certain tendencies in your spoken language. Here are four consistent
conditions that are a result of intonation's tense peaks and relaxed
valleys. 1. Reduced Vowels You were introduced to reduced vowels in Chapter 1.
They appear in the valleys that are formed by the strong peaks of intonation. The
more you reduce the words in the valleys, the smoother and more natural your speech
will sound. A characteristic of reduced vowels is that your throat muscles should
be very relaxed. This will allow the unstressed vowels to reduce toward the
schwa. Neutral vowels take less energy and muscularity to produce than tense vowels.
For example, the word unbelievable should only have one hard vowel, unbelievable. 2.
Voiced consonants The mouth muscles are relaxed to create a voiced sound like Z or
D. For unvoiced consonants such as S or T, they are sharp and tense. Relaxing your
muscles will simultaneously reduce your vowels and voice your consonants. Think of
voiced consonants as reduced consonants. Both reduced consonants and reduced vowels
are unconsciously preferred by a native speaker of American English. This explains
why T so frequently becomes D and S becomes Z. Get it, Izda. 3. Like sound
with like sound. It's not easy to change horses midstream, so when you have a
voiced consonant, let the consonant that follows it be voiced as well. In the verb
used, for example, the S is really a Z, so it's followed by D. The phrase used to, on
the other hand, has a real S, so it's followed by T. Vowels are, by definition,
voiced. So when one is followed by a common, reducible word, it'll change that
word's first sound, like the preposition to, which will change to duh. The only way
to get it is to practice all the time. Again, this will take time. In the
beginning, work on recognizing these patterns when you hear them. When you're
confident that you understand the structure beneath these sounds and you can
intuit where they belong, you can start to try them out. It's not advisable to
memorize one reduced word and stick it into an otherwise overpronounced sentence.
It would sound strange. 4. Relax. You've probably noticed that the preceding three
conditions, as well as other areas that we've covered, such as liaisons and the
schwa, have one thing in common. The idea that it's physically easier this way. This
is one of the most remarkable characteristics of American English. You
need to relax your mouth and throat muscles, except for ah, ah, and other
tense vowels. And let the sounds flow smoothly out. If you find yourself tensing
up, pursing your lips or tightening your throat, you're gonna strangle and lose the
sound you're pursuing. Relax, relax, relax.